Hello, everyone.
大家好。
Welcome back to another podcast here at EnglishPod.
欢迎回到 EnglishPod 的另一期播客。
My name is Marco.
我是 Marco。
And I'm Erica.
我是 Erica。
And today we're looking at another one of our lessons for English of the past decades.
今天我们来看另一节关于过去几十年英语的课程。
And this time, it's the 1990s.
这次是 1990 年代。
Well, you know, the 1990s is a little easier for most of us to remember.
嗯，你知道，90 年代对我们大多数人来说更容易记住。
Yeah, I guess it's a little bit more recent.
是啊，我猜它更近一些。
We're going to be looking at a lot of language that is still used today.
我们会看到很多今天仍在使用的语言。
Most of these words and phrases are still used today.
这些单词和短语大部分今天还在用。
So they're going to be very useful.
所以它们会非常有用。
And you're going to sound a lot more native.
而且你会听起来更像母语者。
A lot cooler as well, huh?
也会更酷，对吧？
Right.
没错。
So before we get started with this lesson, why don't we take a look at vocabulary preview?
在我们开始这节课之前，不如先看看词汇预览？
Vocabulary preview.
词汇预览。
We have two words we're going to hear in the dialogue.
我们有两个词会在对话中听到。
Now the first one is a mall.
第一个是 mall。
A mall.
Mall。
M-A-L-L, mall.
M-A-L-L，mall。
All right, so a mall is basically short for shopping mall.
好的，mall 基本上是 shopping mall 的简称。
And a shopping mall is a big building with many stores inside.
而 shopping mall 是一个里面有很多商店的大建筑。
Right.
对。
So it's like a shopping center.
所以它就像一个购物中心。
And our last word for vocabulary preview is gang.
词汇预览的最后一个词是 gang。
The gang.
The gang。
Okay, so a gang is a group of people, right?
好的，gang 是一群人，对吧？
Yeah, it's a group of people.
是的，是一群人。
You can call your friends the gang.
你可以叫你的朋友们 the gang。
We're going to go out with the gang tonight.
我们今晚要和 gang 一起出去。
Yep.
对。
And we sometimes hear this word and it has a negative meaning, right?
我们有时听到这个词有负面含义，对吧？
Right, like street gang.
对，比如 street gang（街头帮派）。
Yeah, so people who fight and deal drugs and all that sort of stuff.
是的，就是那些打架、贩毒之类的人。
Right.
对。
So it can have a negative and a positive meaning, but it just depends on how you use it.
所以它既有负面也有正面含义，取决于你怎么用。
Yeah, but in the dialogue we'll hear it with a positive meaning.
是的，但在对话中我们会听到正面含义。
Right.
对。
So that's all the words we have for vocabulary preview.
这就是词汇预览的所有词。
Let's listen to this cool and hip dialogue from the 1990s and we'll come back later and
让我们听听这个 90 年代酷炫的对话，稍后回来解释一些词。
explain some words.
解释一些词。
Hey, Four Eyes.
嘿，四眼。
What's up, man?
怎么了，哥们？
How have you been?
你最近怎么样？
Not bad.
还不错。
Just went to the mall and picked up some junk.
刚去了商场，买了些小玩意儿。
Check out my new Adidas.
看看我的新阿迪达斯。
Those are dope.
那些真酷。
You are going to be getting mad props from the gang, man.
你会从哥们那儿得到很多赞赏的，老兄。
Anyways, have you seen Betty lately?
对了，你最近见过贝蒂吗？
Dude, don't even go there.
哥们，别提那事。
That girl started tripping because I went to the movies with Veronica the other day.
那女孩开始发飙，因为我前几天和维罗妮卡去看电影了。
I was like, look, you knew how I was before you got with me.
我就说，听着，你跟我在一起之前就知道我是什么样的人。
That's right.
没错。
You are such a player, man.
你真是个花花公子，老兄。
Dude, there's Mad Max.
哥们，那是疯狂麦克斯。
Let's go say hi.
我们去打个招呼吧。
Mad Max, what's up?
疯狂麦克斯，怎么了？
Are you okay?
你还好吗？
You look like you just saw a ghost.
你看起来像见了鬼一样。
I got an F in English class.
我英语课得了 F。
My life is over.
我的人生完了。
Dude, you're over it.
哥们，你想太多了。
You need to lay off the books for a while and have some fun.
你需要暂时放下书本，找点乐子。
Come on, let's bounce.
来吧，我们走吧。
Where are we going?
我们去哪儿？
Oh, crap.
哦，糟了。
My dad is going to go postal when he finds out about this.
我爸要是知道这事，肯定会发疯的。
I'm going to open the can of whoop ass on you if you don't come with me right now.
你要是不马上跟我走，我就揍扁你。
Okay, okay.
好吧，好吧。
Geez.
天哪。
Well, it sounds like this guy's got some problems at school, huh?
嗯，听起来这家伙在学校有些麻烦，是吧？
Yeah, he got an F on his paper, but you always can count on your friends to try and cheer
是啊，他论文得了 F，但你总能指望朋友想办法让你振作起来。
you up by doing something.
你振作起来。
Yeah, but they use some really great phrases and vocabulary words, so why don't we look
是啊，但他们用了一些很棒的短语和词汇，所以我们不如现在在“语言要点”里看看这些。
at those now in Language Takeaway.
语言要点。
Language Takeaway.
All right, on Language Takeaway we're going to be looking at five words and well, let's
好的，在语言要点里，我们会看五个词，嗯，让我们从第一个开始。
start with the first one.
从第一个开始。
So the guy was talking about his really cool new shoes, his new Adidas, right?
所以那家伙在说他很酷的新鞋，他的新阿迪达斯，对吧？
And his friend said, those are dope.
他朋友说，那些真酷。
Dope.
Dope。
Okay, so it's pretty easy to understand when something is dope.
好的，理解什么东西是 dope 很容易。
It's really awesome.
它真的很棒。
It's cool.
很酷。
It's great.
很好。
Right, it's great.
对，很好。
So that's dope.
所以那就是 dope。
And it's an adjective, right?
而且它是形容词，对吧？
So his friend said, those are dope.
所以他朋友说，那些真酷。
And he said, you're going to be getting mad props from the gang.
然后他说，你会从哥们那儿得到很多赞赏。
Okay, so mad props.
好的，所以 mad props。
Mad props.
Mad props。
We can divide this word in two.
我们可以把这个词分成两部分。
So let's take a look at the first part, mad.
先看第一部分，mad。
So we understand that mad is angry, right?
我们理解 mad 是生气的意思，对吧？
Yeah, but it can also mean a lot, right?
是的，但它也可以表示很多，对吧？
Or like amazing.
或者像很棒。
Or really.
或者非常。
So if I say, you have mad skills.
所以如果我说，你有 mad skills。
You're really good at something.
你真的很擅长某事。
Or you can say, she has a mad amount of shoes.
或者你可以说，她有 mad amount of shoes。
All right.
好的。
So he's going to get mad props.
所以他会得到 mad props。
Now props is like respect or compliments.
现在 props 就像尊重或赞美。
Yeah.
是的。
So his shoes are so cool that he's going to get a lot of respect or a lot of compliments
所以他的鞋太酷了，他会从朋友那儿得到很多尊重或赞美。
from his friends.
很多赞美。
Exactly.
没错。
Mad props.
Mad props。
So they started talking about girls and he mentioned that this girl started tripping.
然后他们开始谈论女孩，他提到这女孩开始 tripping。
Tripping.
Tripping。
So to trip.
所以 to trip。
Right.
对。
As you notice, it's trippin'.
如你所见，它是 trippin'。
It doesn't have the G at the end, which isn't really grammatically correct, but that's kind
结尾没有 G，这在语法上不太正确，但发音就是这样。
of the way it's pronounced.
发音就是这样。
Yeah.
是的。
We would never say the G. Right.
我们永远不会发那个 G 的音。对。
So if somebody is trippin'.
所以如果有人 trippin'。
They're getting really upset.
他们变得非常沮丧。
They're getting really angry.
他们变得非常生气。
Right.
对。
They're causing trouble.
他们在找麻烦。
So why don't we listen to a couple of examples of how we could use trippin' for different
所以我们不如听几个例子，看看 trippin' 在不同情况下怎么用。
situations.
不同情况。
Example one.
例子一。
Leanne was trippin' because I got dirt on her car.
Leanne 在 trippin'，因为我把泥弄到她车上了。
Example two.
例子二。
Even though I apologized for calling her fat, Jeannie was trippin' all night.
尽管我因为叫她胖而道歉，Jeannie 整晚都在 trippin'。
Example three.
例子三。
He sent me 43 text messages and called me about 20 times.
他给我发了 43 条短信，还打了大约 20 次电话。
That guy is trippin' over me.
那家伙在为我 trippin'。
Okay, so that's pretty clear.
好的，这很清楚。
Trippin'.
Trippin'。
All right.
好的。
Now, moving on to our next word.
现在，继续下一个词。
They wanted to go somewhere and he said, come on, let's bounce.
他们想去某个地方，他说，来吧，let's bounce。
Let's bounce.
Let's bounce。
I'm gonna bounce.
I'm gonna bounce。
Now, bounce basically means let's leave.
现在，bounce 基本上意思是离开。
Yeah.
是的。
Let's get out of here.
我们离开这里。
But we might be more familiar with this word as in like a ball, right?
但我们可能更熟悉这个词像球一样，对吧？
A ball bounces off the floor.
球从地板上弹起来。
Exactly.
没错。
So I guess it's kind of the same.
所以我猜有点类似。
You kind of bounce off the floor and leave that place.
你有点像从地板上弹起来然后离开那个地方。
Yeah.
是的。
Let's bounce.
Let's bounce。
Okay, so for our final word.
好的，最后一个词。
Now, this guy who got a bad mark on his paper, he was nervous about what his dad would say,
现在，这个论文得了低分的家伙，他担心他爸爸会说什么，对吧？
right?
对。
Right.
因为他爸爸要 go postal。
Because his dad was going to go postal.
他说，我爸爸要 go postal。
He said, my dad is gonna go postal.
To go postal。
To go postal.
现在，如果你 go postal，意思是发疯。
Now, if you go postal, it means you go crazy.
是的，你真的失控。
Yeah, you really freak out.
你变得非常生气。
You get very angry.
是的，像非常生气。
Yeah, like really angry.
非常生气。
This word comes from the 90s because during a time, it was very common in the United States
这个词来自 90 年代，因为有一段时间，在美国，邮政工人、邮递员经常有点发疯，开始开枪射人，送一些奇怪的包裹。
that postal workers, mailmen, were going a little bit crazy and they started shooting
送一些奇怪的包裹。
people and delivering some strange packages.
嗯，我猜在邮局工作的人可能工作不太有趣，这让他们有点疯狂。
Well, I guess so people who work in the post office maybe don't have the most exciting
让他们有点疯狂。
jobs and that drives them a little crazy.
没错。
Exactly.
But now they have a term named after them.
但现在他们有了一个以他们命名的术语。
All right.
好的。
So why don't we listen to our dialogue for the second time?
所以我们不如再听一遍对话？
We're going to slow it down a little bit and then we'll come back.
我们会放慢一点速度，然后回来。
Hey, Four Eyes.
嘿，四眼。
What's up, man?
怎么了，哥们？
How have you been?
你最近怎么样？
Not bad.
还不错。
Just went to the mall and picked up some junk.
刚去了商场，买了些小玩意儿。
Check out my new Adidas.
看看我的新阿迪达斯。
Those are dope.
那些真酷。
You are going to be getting mad props from the gang, man.
你会从哥们那儿得到很多赞赏的，老兄。
Anyways, have you seen Betty lately?
对了，你最近见过贝蒂吗？
Dude, don't even go there.
哥们，别提那事。
That girl started tripping because I went to the movies with Veronica the other day.
那女孩开始发飙，因为我前几天和维罗妮卡去看电影了。
I was like, look, you knew how I was before you got with me.
我就说，听着，你跟我在一起之前就知道我是什么样的人。
That's right.
没错。
You are such a player, man.
你真是个花花公子，老兄。
Dude, there's Mad Max.
哥们，那是疯狂麦克斯。
Let's go say hi.
我们去打个招呼吧。
Max, what's up?
麦克斯，怎么了？
Are you okay?
你还好吗？
You look like you just saw a ghost.
你看起来像见了鬼一样。
I got an F in English class.
我英语课得了 F。
My life is over.
我的人生完了。
Dude, you're over it.
哥们，你想太多了。
You need to lay off the books for a while and have some fun.
你需要暂时放下书本，找点乐子。
Come on, let's bounce.
来吧，我们走吧。
Where are we going?
我们要去哪儿？
Oh, crap.
哦，糟了。
My dad is going to go postal when he finds out about this.
我爸要是发现这事，肯定会暴跳如雷。
I'm going to open a can of whoop-ass on you if you don't come with me right now.
你要是不马上跟我走，我就揍扁你。
Okay, okay.
好吧，好吧。
Jeez.
天哪。
Okay, so I think that was a little easier to understand.
好吧，我觉得刚才那段稍微好理解一点。
You know, we've got a lot of pretty strange words and phrases, some interesting slang.
你知道，我们有很多相当奇怪的单词和短语，还有一些有趣的俚语。
Yeah, and I want to take a look at this slang now, so let's get started with Fluency Builder.
是啊，我现在想看看这些俚语，那我们就从流利度构建器开始吧。
Fluency Builder.
流利度构建器。
Okay, so the guy with the new shoes, he asked his friends, have you seen Betty lately, right?
好，那个穿新鞋的家伙问他的朋友，你最近见过贝蒂吗，对吧？
Right.
对。
And his friend replied, don't even go there.
他朋友回答说，别提那茬。
Right.
对。
And he said, dude, don't even go there.
他说，哥们，别提那茬。
Don't even go there.
别提那茬。
So what does he mean when he says, don't even go there?
那他说“别提那茬”是什么意思？
He means, don't talk about it.
他的意思是，别谈这个。
I don't want to talk about it.
我不想谈这个。
Right.
对。
Don't even touch that subject.
别碰那个话题。
Don't even mention it.
别提它。
Right.
对。
So if somebody wants to talk about a topic that you think is sensitive or you don't want
所以如果有人想聊一个你觉得敏感或不想
to talk about, just say, hey, don't even go there.
聊的话题，就说，嘿，别提那茬。
So Marco, what do you think about the new tax law?
那么马可，你对新税法怎么看？
Don't even go there.
别提那茬。
I don't even want to talk about politics.
我根本不想谈政治。
Okay.
好吧。
I think that's a really actually quite helpful phrase to avoid talking about an uncomfortable
我觉得这其实是个很有用的短语，可以避免谈论一个令人不舒服的
subject.
话题。
Right.
对。
So he said, don't even go there.
所以他说了“别提那茬”。
And he started talking about the girl and she was tripping.
然后他开始谈论那个女孩，她当时在发飙。
And then he said something interesting.
然后他说了句有趣的话。
He said, I was like, look, you knew how I was before you got with me.
他说，我当时就说，听着，你跟我在一起之前就知道我是什么样的人。
Yeah, I really like this phrase.
是啊，我真的很喜欢这个短语。
Now, I want to focus on the first part.
现在，我想先关注第一部分。
I was like.
我当时就说。
Now, you might hear a lot of native English speakers use these three words before they
现在，你可能会听到很多英语母语者在
start telling you what they said.
开始告诉你他们说了什么之前，先用这三个词。
So it's like saying, I said or I told him.
这就像在说“我说”或“我告诉他”。
Yep.
是的。
So this actually is really common, especially with people under the age of 30.
所以这其实非常常见，尤其是在30岁以下的人群中。
So why don't we hear a few more examples of how it's used now.
那我们不如现在听几个例子，看看它是怎么用的。
Example one.
例子一。
This guy caused a car accident.
这家伙引发了一场车祸。
I was like, you idiot.
我当时就说，你这个白痴。
You can kill people by driving like that.
你那样开车会害死人的。
Example two.
例子二。
And then I was like, I hate you.
然后我当时就说，我恨你。
And she was all like, I hate you more.
她当时就说，我更恨你。
Example three.
例子三。
I told the teacher that I didn't finish my homework and he was like, I'll see you after
我告诉老师我没完成作业，他当时就说，放学后
school.
见。
So if you're telling a story or you're maybe talking to somebody and you want to explain
所以如果你在讲故事，或者可能跟某人聊天，想解释
what you said, you can say, I was like, hey, what are you doing?
你说了什么，你可以说，我当时就说，嘿，你在干嘛？
And she was like, what?
她当时就说，什么？
So you can have an entire dialogue based with I was like, she was like, we were like.
所以你可以用“我当时就说”、“她当时就说”、“我们当时就说”来组成一整段对话。
Okay.
好吧。
So I was like, it's super, super useful.
所以“我当时就说”超级、超级有用。
So now our next word.
那么现在看下一个词。
Now, they saw their friend who got the bad marking in school and the guy said, dude,
现在，他们看到了那个在学校成绩很糟的朋友，那家伙说，哥们，
get over it.
别纠结了。
Get over it.
So if somebody tells you to get over it.
所以如果有人叫你“别纠结了”。
Stop worrying about it.
就是别担心了。
Okay.
好吧。
Or stop thinking about it.
或者别想了。
All right.
好的。
So if somebody is sad because maybe his girlfriend broke up with him, you would say, get over
所以如果有人因为女朋友跟他分手而难过，你会说，别纠结
it.
了。
Stop thinking about it.
别想了。
Let it go.
放下吧。
It's in the past.
都过去了。
Yeah.
是啊。
And you commonly use this for when somebody is upset about a small thing, something they
你通常用这个短语，是当有人为一件小事、一件他们
shouldn't worry about.
不该担心的事而烦恼时。
Get over it.
别纠结了。
Yep.
是的。
Now, why don't we go on to our final word?
现在，我们继续看最后一个词吧？
At the end of the dialogue, they said, I'm going to open a can of whoop ass.
在对话结尾，他们说，我要揍扁你。
Okay.
好吧。
So to open a can of whoop ass on somebody.
所以“要揍扁某人”。
To open a can of whoop ass.
要揍扁。
So again, let's break this down before we explain it.
所以再说一次，我们在解释之前先分解一下。
Okay.
好吧。
I think we have to take one step back here.
我觉得我们得先退一步。
To whoop someone's ass is to beat them up, right?
“揍某人屁股”就是痛打他们一顿，对吧？
Right.
对。
To punch them and hurt them.
就是揍他们，伤害他们。
Right.
对。
So to whoop somebody's ass.
所以是“揍某人的屁股”。
So if I open a can of whoop ass, what does that mean?
那么如果我说“我要打开一罐揍人罐头”，那是什么意思？
It means you're going to beat them up.
意思是你准备要揍他们。
So it's just a funny, very informal way of saying like, in this can, I'm going to open
所以这只是个有趣、非常不正式的说法，就像说，在这个罐子里，我要打开
it and I'm going to start hitting you or something like that.
它，然后开始打你之类的。
Some sort of small man is going to jump out of the can and start hitting you.
某种小人会从罐子里跳出来开始打你。
Exactly.
正是。
But it's never literal.
但这从来都不是字面意思。
It's not like you're actually going to beat somebody up.
并不是你真的要打某人一顿。
It's just kind of like a joke.
这有点像开玩笑。
Yeah.
是啊。
It's an empty threat.
这是个空洞的威胁。
Yeah.
是啊。
All right.
好的。
So some really interesting words and phrases in this dialogue.
所以这段对话里有一些非常有趣的单词和短语。
I think we should listen to it for the last time and then we'll come back and talk a little
我觉得我们应该最后再听一遍，然后回来再聊一聊
bit more about this great decade.
这个伟大的十年。
Hey, Four Eyes.
嘿，四眼。
What's up, man?
怎么了，老兄？
How have you been?
你最近怎么样？
Not bad.
还不错。
Just went to the mall and picked up some junk.
刚去了趟商场，买了些小玩意儿。
Check out my new Adidas.
看看我的新阿迪达斯。
Those are dope.
真酷。
You are going to be getting mad props from the gang, man.
你肯定会从兄弟们那里得到很多赞赏的，老兄。
Anyways, have you seen Betty lately?
对了，你最近见过贝蒂吗？
Dude, don't even go there.
哥们，别提那茬。
That girl started tripping because I went to the movies with Veronica the other day.
那女孩开始发飙，因为我前几天和维罗妮卡去看电影了。
I was like, look, you knew how I was before you got with me.
我当时就说，听着，你跟我在一起之前就知道我是什么样的人。
That's right.
没错。
You are such a player, man.
你真是个花花公子，老兄。
Dude, there's Mad Max.
哥们，那是疯狂麦克斯。
Let's go say hi.
我们去打个招呼吧。
Max, what's up?
麦克斯，怎么了？
Are you okay?
你还好吗？
You look like you just saw a ghost.
你看起来像见了鬼一样。
I got an F in English class.
我英语课得了不及格。
My life is over.
我的人生完了。
Dude, you're over it.
哥们，别纠结了。
You need to lay off the books for a while and have some fun.
你需要暂时放下书本，找点乐子。
Come on, let's bounce.
来吧，我们撤。
Where are we going?
我们要去哪儿？
Oh, crap.
哦，糟了。
My dad is going to go postal when he finds out about this.
我爸要是发现这事，肯定会暴跳如雷。
I'm going to open a can of whoop-ass on you if you don't come with me right now.
你要是不马上跟我走，我就揍扁你。
Okay, okay.
好吧，好吧。
Geez.
天哪。
Well, Marco, in the dialogue, I heard one of the guys say, what's up?
嗯，马可，在对话里，我听到其中一个家伙说“怎么了？”
But he said it in a really strange way, didn't he?
但他说得方式很奇怪，对吧？
Yeah, exactly.
是啊，没错。
He said, what's up?
他说的是“咋了？”
Okay.
好吧。
So what's up with that?
所以这是怎么回事？
So in the 90s, it was popular instead of saying what's up, you would just kind of double the
所以在90年代，流行不说“怎么了”，而是把
S and just say what's up.
S音拖长，说成“咋了”。
And then it became very famous with a TV commercial for a certain beer.
然后因为某个啤酒的电视广告而变得非常有名。
And actually, I remember this commercial during the Super Bowl.
实际上，我记得超级碗期间的这则广告。
They had this big commercial where everyone was saying what's up in this really strange
他们有个大广告，里面每个人都用这种奇怪的方式说“咋了”，
way, right?
对吧？
It's still used today informally between friends.
现在朋友之间非正式场合仍然在用。
You'll go ahead, hey, what's up?
你会说，嘿，咋了？
What's up?
咋了？
Yeah, you'll use it.
是啊，你会用。
Yeah, so that commercial made it actually quite cool and famous to talk like that.
是啊，所以那个广告让那样说话变得很酷、很有名。
Actually in SpanishPod, they have a show called Que Pasa, which is like the translation of
实际上在SpanishPod里，他们有个节目叫Que Pasa，就像
what's up.
“怎么了”的翻译。
Oh, right.
哦，对。
They start each show with like saying, Que Pasa, but it's exactly the same.
他们每期节目开头都会说Que Pasa，但完全一样。
So maybe it will become popular in Spanish.
所以也许它在西班牙语里也会流行起来。
Maybe but I guess only...
也许吧，但我猜只有……
Time will tell.
时间会证明。
Yeah, that's right.
是啊，没错。
All right.
好的。
So really cool stuff.
所以真的很酷。
And as we heard typical music from the 90s.
而且我们听到了典型的90年代音乐。
And another interesting thing was the nicknames, Four Eyes, Mad Max, very popular among young
另一个有趣的事情是绰号，四眼、疯狂麦克斯，在年轻
kids.
孩子中很流行。
So remember, if you have any questions about this language or anything else about this
所以记住，如果你对这节课的语言或任何其他内容有疑问，
lesson, come to our website at EnglishPod.com.
请访问我们的网站EnglishPod.com。
Right.
对。
You can leave all your questions and comments there and we hope to see you guys there.
你可以在那里留下所有问题和评论，我们希望能在那里见到你们。
So thanks for listening and until next time.
所以感谢收听，下次再见。
Goodbye.
再见。
Because you won't say goodbye until Und card is gone.
因为你不会说再见，直到Und卡消失。